<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The x86 Blog</title>
    <description>A Computer is an instrument whose music is ideas
</description>
    <link>http://x86.rocks/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://x86.rocks/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 20:26:15 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 20:26:15 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Functional Programming in the Cloud</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;functions-as-a-service&quot;&gt;Functions as a Service&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional programming paradigm has been around for quite some time and its very popular in programming circles but its use had remain limited to academia and some very esoteric use cases. But recently, there has been a new found interest in this paradigm in Cloud space and every vendor either has an offering around it or slated to have one. In this post we will examine why functional paradigm is more relevant in cloud and how we can take benefit of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let’s see what functional programming is at 50,000 ft. Its a philosophy in which a method/function does not have side effect and does not alter the global state of an object. The functions which adhere to this philosophy are called pure functions and they are idempotent in a sense that they can be executed n number of times and there output will remain the same when same parameters are passed. Mathematically speaking&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-mathml&quot; data-lang=&quot;mathml&quot;&gt;f(x,y) =&amp;gt; {z}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i.e. An output of a function f taking parameter x &amp;amp; y will always map to a set z. Some example of very popular modern functional programming languages are Haskell and Scala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how they are relevant to the Cloud? Ask any Cloud Sales Executive and they would reply (and I quote) &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Better Scalability, Better Manageability, Keeping Operational Costs in Check&lt;/code&gt; and some of the seasoned ones will also throw in buzz words like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Agility, HIPAA/NIST/FedRAMP Compliance, Better Line of Sight on IT infrastructure cost centers&lt;/code&gt; etc. While these may sound as pure demagoguery, they do have some truth in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;Functions As A Service or FaaS&lt;/strong&gt; as I like to call them (there, I threw in one of my one buzz words), you write  a function which is invoked every time a specific event occurs. Once the event is &lt;em&gt;serviced&lt;/em&gt;, the underlying infrastructure on which it is executed &lt;em&gt;disappears&lt;/em&gt;. Think about it in this way, there is a container inside which your code executes in response to an event and once that event is handled your container will be disposed of if there are no more events to handle. If multiple events occur at the same time then one container is created to handle each of the event and the Cloud will take care of requesting routing, load balancing and resource management. And what are the sources of these events? These events could stem from a range of sources like a Rest API call, a monitoring alert created on a resource like a VM, a message sent to a message queue, a database trigger, a scheduled task or a chron job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an example of the recently concluded Brexit referendum. Say for example, all British citizens are required to either download an App or login to the British government website to cast there vote (authentication and singularity of each vote is left as exercise to the reader). If you are an infrastructure guy then you have already sweated over the load backend services for the App &amp;amp; Website will have to face. Now, assume that the logic of recording a vote is implemented as an AWS Lambda and an API is hooked up with it and every time some one would cast a vote a Lambda function would be executed and the vote will be recorded in AWS Dynamo DB or Azure Document DB. With this solution whole referendum process could virtually be completed without having to deploy a single server IaaS or PaaS for backend services. Sounds to good to be true, right? At the time of writing this none of the FaaS offering are infinitely scalable, they do have limits attached to them but you could get around them using throttling or via multi-region deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how is this beneficial in terms of all the “bilities”? With FaaS all you have to do is select a runtime (NodeJS, Python, etc.), amount of RAM and an execution timeout after which your code would be terminated. But isn’t this similar to PaaS? No &amp;amp; Yes. No because you don’t have to setup load balancing or worry about an instance failing due to resource quench etc. And yes because just like PaaS you need to select underlying runtime and some resource allocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the major distinction over  here is, your FaaS container won’t hang around forever if it has nothing to do and you will always have enough containers executing to service your load and your function executes only in response to an event, you can’t start a server here and actively listen for requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s are some of the FaaS offerings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amazon WebServices - &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/welcome.html&quot;&gt;Lambda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IBM BlueMix - &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.ibm.com/openwhisk/&quot;&gt;OpenWhisk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Microsoft Azure - &lt;a href=&quot;https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/services/functions/&quot;&gt;Functions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;auth0 - &lt;a href=&quot;https://webtask.io/&quot;&gt;Webtask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So fire up your favorite Cloud today and give functional paradigm a spin.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2016 14:19:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://x86.rocks/aws%20lambda/functional%20programming/cloud/azure%20functions/2016/06/25/Functional-Programming-in-the-Cloud.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://x86.rocks/aws%20lambda/functional%20programming/cloud/azure%20functions/2016/06/25/Functional-Programming-in-the-Cloud.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>AWS Lambda</category>
        
        <category>Functional Programming</category>
        
        <category>Cloud</category>
        
        <category>Azure Functions</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>AWS API Gateway + Lambda gotchas</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;aws-api-gateway--lambda-gotchas&quot;&gt;AWS API Gateway + Lambda gotchas&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AWS API Gateway&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AWS Lambda&lt;/code&gt; makes it possible to create a serverless backend architecture. While this has opened a whole new bunch of possiblities in terms of scaling vis-a-vis cost saving, there are several technical and architectural gotchas one must address to fully utilize them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This post talks about pitfalls I encountered while working with API Gateway and Lambda, if you are new to this subject then read this nice blogpost from TechCrunch &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2015/11/24/aws-lamda-makes-serverless-applications-a-reality/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-iam-role-assumption-blues&quot;&gt;The IAM role assumption blues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your API gateway endpoint needs to &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt; the IAM role which you had provided and API Gateway, like any other service, must have permission to assume this role. AWS documentation clearly mentions this, however, it’s easy to overlook this while in haste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open the IAM console and select the role which you want your API to assume for Lambda execution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click on Trust Relationship tab and click on edit, on the screen which follows allow API Gateway service Id “apigateway.amazonwaws.com” to assume this IAM role by adding the following statement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Sid&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;   
		&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Effect&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Allow&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Principal&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Service&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;apigateway.amazonaws.com&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Action&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;sts:AssumeRole&quot;&lt;/span&gt;  
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if you are using other AWS services like CloudWatch or S3, then your IAM role should have permission to execute these services too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-nodejs-zip-package-must-have-packagejson-file&quot;&gt;Your nodejs zip package must have &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For NodeJS if you are uploading a zip file containing source code then your zip file must contain a package.json file and it must indicate the &lt;strong&gt;main&lt;/strong&gt; source code file. Otherwise AWS Lambda will probably throw an error indicating that it could not find the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;index.handler&lt;/code&gt; (or whatever function name configured as the event handler). For e.g., assuming your main file is index, add this line to your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;main&quot;: &quot;index.js&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;limited-disk-access&quot;&gt;Limited disk access&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Lambda does allow you to upload custom binaries in your package and execute them, it does not allow you to read local files or access any other directories except &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/tmp&lt;/code&gt;. If you attempt to do so you would encounter an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;EOPEN&lt;/code&gt;  while opening a file and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;EACCES&lt;/code&gt; while creating directories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the storage space provided by Lambda is ephemeral and limited to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;500 MBs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; at this time, for persistence storage AWS recommends using S3 but any other cloud storage solution like Azure Blob Storage can be used&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forums.aws.amazon.com/thread.jspa?messageID=595370&quot;&gt;Better Together: Amazon ECS and AWS Lambda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2016 14:19:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://x86.rocks/aws/aws%20api%20gateway/lambda/2016/03/26/API-Gateway-+-Lambda-gotcahs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://x86.rocks/aws/aws%20api%20gateway/lambda/2016/03/26/API-Gateway-+-Lambda-gotcahs.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>AWS</category>
        
        <category>AWS API Gateway</category>
        
        <category>Lambda</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
